software engineering radio episode 120. oh this is software engineering radio,
the podcast for professional developers on the web at se - radio dotnet.
I see radio brings you relevant and detailed discussions and interviews on software engineering topics every 10 days.
thanks to our audience and the partners listed on our website possible.
[Music]
so Hanukkah welcome to our show. I just got some rubber yo please introduce yourself to our audience.
yes hello, my name is anneka clapper.
I've been involved in the UML 1.1 that was actually the first version to be.
specified as a standard. and I've been also involved in the development of the object constraint language, also known as ocl.
and I've also did some work on mdaa model-driven architecture.
and currently my focuses on domain-specific languages.
okay clear, well you. mentioned ocl already.
um could you tell us a bit more about your whole involvement with ocl, how this is a thing gets started?
yeah well I've been working with object-oriented modeling from the early 90s.
and I was very familiar with what is now called to the class diagram.
and well it seemed to be.
that you couldn't express any everything that you wanted and needed to express about an application in that class diagram.
and found not talking about dynamics things you put in activity diagrams or state diagrams. but more aesthetic things that.
you'd like to add to class diagrams, which are also very important.
like the age of a person may not be less than zero.
very important stuff when you talk to database administrators, they always know what you are talking about.
yes and so.
we decided to find a way to add a way to class diagrams to.
specify these types of what we are called then called constraints.
so it's actually really something that is restricting the class diagram so that you have few instances which are actually valid.
so I mean what what were your influences in creating ocl?
I mean did you start from scratch, were already existing stuff that. you inspire by?
yep, we of course we were inspired by what was previously available.
we were inspired first by the work in the programming language iPhone with the pre and post conditions and.
invariants.
we were also inspired by the programming language small talk in the way that you can build expressions.
and we were also inspired by the work that was already done in IBM at that moment own business process modeling.
business modeling, and in IBM at the time people thought it was very important.
that business people should be able to.
express these types of constraints in the way that they really meant them.
in the language that these big business people use.
and from these three starting points on, we and of course the UML class diagram, we created a language.
and of course all type of background stuff like set.
theory from mathematics and things like that.
actually everything we had in our package we took into account in building yourself.
and I keep referring to we because I. did not do that alone.
I think that with my colleague your swarmer.
of course you mentioned the IBM initiative that was targeted at enabling businesspeople to come up with the constraints.
versus a a target for you as well when you started out together videos working on ocl?
no not really, this has been a dream in in IT for so many years, for 40 years or so.
to have the business people express what the application should do.
and I'd really don't believe in that,.
we will never be there.
but we do need simpler ways to express these type of things because.
the business people require more and more complex things to be. expressed.
you know in in the in the sixties when people started to think about well business people should write programs.
then the programs were so simple, you know that indeed if you had a mathematical background you could write programs.
but now the demands on IT are much higher and we need to express more complex things.
so the IT people need new languages to express the business stuff. yeah, in a better and more efficient way.
yeah yeah, I guess the subject will pop up later when we talk about your current activities.
absolutely, you mentioned Ifill and and small talk as an inspiration.
but ocl ended up looking differently from those languages, no yes?
is there a reason behind it?
you know the reason why I'm asking is because I think that generally, I.
know not hoping him I'm telling on any toes here.
but people tend to find ocl difficult, more difficult than they probably tend to take an eyeful or a small talk for instance.
is a do today to the influence of the set theory that you mentioned earlier that you infuse that on the language?
yes it probably is.
the ideas we took from small talk was that you can put one expression after the other using a dot notation. and so.
you can build a very very large expression.
yeah and if every expression needs to have a resulting value yeah to be. able to do that.
and when you combine that.
with things from set theory like take the subset of this sets.
but leave out half of the members based on some expression.
then you really get this complex well what people find to complex notation nowadays.
but actually it's not a very complex one if you really look at it,
it's it's actually very similar to SQL, only SQL is more you have to write more.
yeah when you write SQL and shells are a condensed your anguish.
ice plot is more of an narrative language, it is like you were writing a story more or less.
maybe that helps people in. yeah because I.
I've always always been confused by the relatively lack of uptake on ocl.
and they're relatively large of take on and on sequel people that were more or less proficient in sequel.
we're not so when I was here and I was always bothered by that.
this indeed could be a year phenomena.
yeah yeah, it's a very condensed language.
but there's also another difference between SQL and oshio. and that is that.
well SQL really takes the godlike position if you like from the object-oriented point of view.
you know everything is available, everything is visible.
and LCL takes an object-oriented a point of view, you come from a certain object.
and you can see within the context of that object some stuff.
yeah and then you navigate through all of the data that you have here.
so that's also a very important difference which people tend to find difficult.
yeah yeah I can see that.
so how would you describe the influence of OC, oh are you happy, did you succeed and what you set out to do? yeah I'm happy with the sale absolutely,
it it is taken up especially by the academic community, they're not so much in in IT practice I think.
but maybe that's one step too many.
but it does influence thinking about languages.
for instance.
in Java five you have the collections that are typed by the element type.
yeah well I shall have that a long time before.
yeah and I really believe that then the requests for those typed collections come from people who have a look at LC unfold.
well that's a good thing, we really really like that.
I know we need that.
we still see your future 400 CEO who has the window closed.
I see a future nurse she'll actually as I've always done not in the language itself.
the language itself will probably die in 1020 years as long as you do as languages do.
but I see a large future in in the concepts that we introduced.
working with these collections is very easy in LCL. and you see that.
again in Java 5, there's a much simpler way of expressing loops over collections, iterations of Elections.
you also see that in c-sharp what I write here and stuff like that. you know bits and.
pieces from the ideas of ocl.
if only the constraints as fact that the thinner the notion that.
when you have a a database schema or a class diagram.
than that you really need to have something else which restricts that diagram to valid instances is very important.
and I see you a large future after that. yes okay that's great.
are there any areas nowadays where you think it should be out of light but isn't?
not specific areas, but I would like it to be. much and much more applied.
if only for building simple if not to say stupid you know models.
yeah everyone who built see you a male model shoot also regard your ocl you know as a useful tool.
but dual support in especially in UML ptosis is lacking with regard to OC oh isn't it?
yes I'm surprised about that because it's it's really very simple to build on our shell parser.
and to give some stool support in the you know to lucious.
if any idea why that is why, why to Randall's just don't seem to see the value that OCR could bring to email modeling?
no I don't have any idea other than it's it's not very demanded by the clients you know.
so it's it's actually there's no demand for it and there's no push for it.
there's no pool and there's no push yeah. and so.
it's it's only there in small parts of the idea world where people really see the use of it.
yeah of course it has popped up in some reincarnation in the qvt standard biology as well.
yes so that's a that has been influenced as well I guess.
and you know fan architecture with in the Czech language yep, which is inspired by Yoshi yoga.
it's not ocl itself isn't it?
it is it is it is should be embarrassed not not be knowing that term some stuff. I should be editing out.
so in in in in inside would you have done something something's different looking back?
no I would have created the same language.
yes that's good absolutely.
what no it's not completely true, what I would like to add is more dynamic stuff to it.
and there you need only have to have a few things like to be. able to instantiate an object.
and well actually if you are able to.
instantiate an object in an AVO expression then you are already much much more powerful.
so stuff like that yeah I really should like to do that.
yeah okay let's close the subject you know CL.
and let's move to your order historical contribution, and the first book on MDA I ever read was by a you and Joe Strummer and Ben bust I believe.
so let's talk a bit about UML and perhaps MDA.
yeah could you tell us a bit about your involvement with the whole MDA thing?
yes of course, well as I said I've been involved in object-oriented modeling for him for a long long time.
but obvious Orion object-oriented modeling doesn't bring you an application, you need to do something by hand.
and I've seen so many programmers and.
you male modelers struggling to do that.
that already very early stages of my career I thought well you. should do this differently.
you should really automate the transition from model to code.
and with the MDA this possibility became a reality.
and I've seen that before already in the early 90s, I've seen that done but only for very small niche domains.
and with the start of MDA it appeared to be.
possible for not only these niche domains but for a very large group of applications.
and that's why I am became so actively involved in model driven development.
we actually involved with the whole OMG in definition of MBA or where you just writing the book?
no I was just writing book.
but of course through my context with the mg I did have their information you know and some inside there.
and why have they lifted but of course I didn't always agree with them.
I actually don't like the distinction of PIM versus PSM.
yes model yeah that's my favorite as well.
yeah I mean if you want to spend a numerous time raising discussions, let's let's discuss the whole independent and dependent stuff.
net whole pattern of course everything is dependent upon something.
yes so actually the question is is what is a platform?
yeah and I don't think the mg has clearly defined the notion of platform.
yeah you also will, you also wrote a book about a UML I believe?
yeah a Dutch one Dutch one, so they also involved in the UML definition by omg.
and the very first stages your mail was created first by Grady Booch and Jim Rambo it irrational.
yeah Ivan Jackson Jacobson didn't join them yeah but later on.
so that was first in 1.0 and actually version 1 of 1 was the first to be. standardized.
and I did some work on that. mhm.
I wasn't in the core team but I had some influence I hope at least my name is on it.
so yeah that's a good thing itself I guess.
so how would you characterize the the impact of MDA being a person who has been involved with MBA from of the fairly beginnings?
the impact of MDA is that now not only a few people know that.
you can generate code from a model.
but actually a large amount of people from the whole of IT industry is aware of.
that. and I don't see that.
a large amount of. people are really doing it.
no still not not no not yet, but they are aware of its civility.
and they are not as reluctant to experiment with it as they were 20 or 15 or 20 years ago.
yeah and that's the good thing I think about it, that's a good thing about MBA.
yeah so it raised the awareness of the whole concept and the whole ideas.
yes we just mentioned, yeah I can see that.
yes and I've always said well it's a matter of generations.
you know it takes 20 years before any a really really gets into the brain of the complete IT industry.
but I think we are well on our track, so that's a positive note absolutely.
okay supera because I are also things that you think that.
it should have had been handled differently in the whole mba creation?
yes I think the expectations were too high too early.
and that's actually what I mean by saying well it takes a generation before this technology really really is ingrained in the whole of the IT industry.
but that means that well you're talking about 20 years or so.
and you can't expect to have all of the advances of MDA within the first three or two years.
you really have to wait these 20 years before you get all of that good stuff, yes out of it.
you have to go to a whole cycle of killed tools coming to the scene and maturing toward to a level of people can actually use them.
yes and yes technically yeah so we are still half rate on the hype cycle so to say.
and your opinion yep, oh maybe not yet halfway we have a few years to go yet.
okay that's a promising thought yep.
so and this is the same goes I guess the same line of questioning for you Mel - I mean you were involved with UML one mm-hmm.
how did you like or experience the creation of UML - well you.
know to the specification or building the specification I only experienced from the outside.
we were during the oshio standard at the time.
and we were actually waiting very long time before the UML specification to be.
finished. and in fact we.
already finished our ocl a specification a long time before the UML specification was completed.
so what I saw from the outside was a large number of discussions which I thought weren't really useful.
and the result is a very very large specification yes.
which I find is not the best thing that could have happened to the world.
yeah I should have preferred a much smaller and much more concise specification.
yeah that is already answering my next question.
I mean as a UML one an MBA practitioner or even a visionary, how would you characterize their the quality of UML - is it useful enough?
well that depends on which side you are on.
from the point of view of a user your mouth hasn't changed much from zero one point zero to two point zero.
that's a good thing here.
so you could say that's a good thing because it's backwards compatible.
but you could also say say that it's not a good thing but we because we don't have enough new elements in the language.
the language doesn't evolve much, so I don't think that's a very positive effect.
actually I'd tend to be.
on the side well we don't have enough evolution in the language.
from the other point of view you can look at the specification and say well is this a good way to.
express this language mm-hmm.
but I didn't like the UML one specification very much.
it was too fake, it was incomplete, was inconsistent at some points.
so it was really a good thing that they changed that.
but the resulting standards the UML 2 standard is as far as I'm concerned too large and.
too complex introduced him to do anything with now.
if you only look at the levels of inheritance hierarchy sometimes you have more than twenty levels and.
of subclasses.
from my knowledge of object-oriented modeling you shouldn't have more than three or four levels of subclasses in a good object-oriented model.
yeah as a rule of thumb. yeah as a rule of thumb exactly.
and that for me means well something's touchy about the specification.
another example is the relatively large amount of different classes of.
things which are only barely different.
if you look at actions for instance.
I believe there's 18 of 20 types of actions.
I don't see a large difference between these actions actually.
the difference is not large enough to really amount to so many different meta classes.
you should have modeled it differently yeah.
but that's coming from my experience with object-oriented modeling and the stuff we've learned from that.
yeah so on these two items from from the user point of view there's not enough evolution.
from the specification point of view a specification is too complex and it's still large.
I'd say well if we really really want a you know three point zero we have to take a completely different direction. do we want the UML 3.0?
well you.
know is a success and it's a good thing to build upon that success.
but only if we can evolve the language.
and at the moment I don't see any new developments in modeling languages.
and I think I work while incorporating in the you know but that also tickles me on the bit of domain-specific languages.
of course perfect cliffhanger is yes of course.
and because their main specific language is do not need to be. general. your mouth of course needs to be.
general, it's a unified your language.
and in a domain-specific language you.
can incorporate much more specific stuff which is useful for a special domain but not in general.
yeah so what what is looming at a horizon in terms of domain-specific languages and the technology involved in it?
well looming on the horizon are a lot large number of domain-specific languages but all really small ones.
and perhaps that's a reason why we don't see them, they creep in as it were.
yeah because there are already a large number of them in specific languages but there are small ones.
they used in one company or in a small domain and they don't get worldwide attention like the UML.
yeah so that is what is its, it is already over the horizon it's coming.
yeah it's actually yeah we can actually see the Horde coming. yes absolutely can be yeah.
it's like a stampede of small domain-specific languages, and and the reason why we don't recognize them is because each one each of them is so very small.
it's a stampede events yeah Stampede events yeah.
of course it's it's kind of the essence of the whole thing that they are kind of small that are very specific to work toward omein.
even a company's interpretation of domain right.
so that their Dayton nullify the need for a universal a modeling language or.
a unified modeling language in your opinion? no I don't think so. because I.
think there are commonalities in every industry in every IT domain.
and we need some way to. express these as well.
and a programming languages are of course good means to do that but they are a bit too low-level mm-hm.
yeah absolutely so I really think that you Mel and Mo specific languages can live next to each other.
okay really gonna think about that scenario.
of course that that that would mean that there would be a universal mechanism of actually communicating between language and language in sis's right? the promise of more for instance?
no it's actually a misconception that.
morph or even EMF can help you there.
Morphin and EMF and any mathematical language is only capable of expressing the specification of a language.
but it's not capable of expressing how languages communicate with each other.
or actually I should be more precise with that because it's not how languages communicate.
languages do not communicate, its then the programs and the models or as I call them the mo grams of a language.
that have real relationships with programs in another language.
and to be.
capable of having these relationships you should build your domain-specific languages in a very specific way.
and currently there are no explicit things explicit concepts in the meta meta languages in wolfin TMF.
that is to express these interrelationships between migrants.
so what do we, yeah you talked about a bit but what concrete technology is there that can be a role in this field if morph and EMF?
and that is something that we still need to invent.
and of course there is some history on this issue as well.
because already in 70s and 80s we were capable of linking in libraries in another language within programs in a specific language like C for instance.
and we can build on that.
but nowadays we need not only include libraries but.
we need to really relate to programs our mo grams in two languages.
and really really needs to have new technologies for that.
in my upcoming book I will explain some of the stuff that.
I've invented to do to do this.
but I'm sure that there are many other ways to do it.
and many of these will prove to be. more effective in the years to come.
ok you been to the terms already a few times mo grams.
describing an upcoming book can you tell us a bit about the book and what it is all about and when it will be released?
the book is at the publisher at the moment.
it will be released in about four months.
and it's um well the title is software language engineering.
so it's really on what a software language is.
and for me as other languages any language that we use to create software with not natural languages but any artificial language.
so because they're artificial languages really we need to explicitly specify them and explain them to people.
and of course any software language has an abstract syntax and economy syntax and semantics like any language.
and for a sovereign language these semantics could be either a code generator or a virtual machine.
so that you can run these mock Rams in this virtual environment.
and actually my book is on that,.
how to explain how to specify abstract syntax.
because that's really the kernel stuff of a language.
the abstract syntax is the most important thing.
how to express concrete syntax in various forms you know textual graphical or combination of both.
how to express the semantics of a language.
what is semantics really because for many people this is a very strange word semantics there.
and I also address well the early stages of how you that.
of the technology of how you can communicate between mo Prime's.
how you can interrelate Milgram's.
and actually this interrelationship is something that you see all the time in programming languages.
you know you have a UML model is just one large chunk,
it's one large piece of well it's not code it's a piece of model. but in in the coding world we.
we've left this type of things are very long time ago.
we've noticed that it's much more simple and so.
much more practical way to.
do things in small bits and pieces which you interrelate with each other.
and we should do that on the modeling level as well.
we should have smaller bits which interrelate.
and the new thing here is that.
we could also interrelate things which are written in different languages.
yes so really chopping your problem in several chunks that operate with each other.
and all those chunks can be written in different languages right?
yes yes and every language you.
choose because it's good a good language to express that type of problem in.
yeah so you could have a language which expresses the screen flow for a web application here.
and you could have a language with expresses your database structure.
well we have several of these of course no but we should relate these to know each other.
yeah and in that.
view I also see a place for the UML next to these large amounts of domain-specific languages.
we could also use your mouth but only for very specific elements of software development. for instance,.
um well I find that the class diagram of UML is very convenient to build well domain schemas in.
yeah but that's only part of an application yeah.
and there are several other bits of UML which are more or less useful.
it depends on on what you really want to express in your application, what type of application you have.
so it really is picking out the good stuff, you stuff the stuff you need for your particular aspect of the overall problem.
yes that's the gist of it right.
yes so with that then enable our age-old dream for getting business people on board.
would this be an opportunity for for that age-old dream?
no no I believe I said this earlier but I don't think we will get business people to do the programming for us.
programming building software is really a very specific task that you should be schools for that,.
you should be educated in doing it. and but we should be able to.
bridge the gap between the ever-rising demands of the business and the application level.
and as far as I'm concerned currently I see that.
the demand side. on the on the business side.
there the rise of the complexity of the demand side.
is much larger than what we are capable of delivering.
and delivering in only itsí.
yeah and that's actually what I see as a as a real problem.
mister anything in what we talked about in this in this interview that could help us in alleviating a problem?
well I think their main specific languages are the way to.
go yeah.
currently there is no other solution for this problem than of domain-specific languages.
in the language of the IT people much much more closer to the language of the businesspeople.
and these two languages will be difference be because the business people will never have the formality that we really need in the IT.
yeah but we should be able to.
bring the two languages much more closer together.
yeah just to bridge the gap that now would know it exists.
yeah yeah make the cat as close as possible she was eating and most easier to jump over together right.
but there will always be a gap that's because I.
find that gap is necessary.
you have to have people that are really not for more and just brainstorming away and doing their stuff the business that you're good at.
and you have these more formal people that aren't really taking these ideas and building applications based on them.
yeah well on on that note having said that.
maybe we should conclude with you expressing your fears and hope for our unknown we'll trade for the foreseeable future.
mm-hmm my hope for the trade is that.
the developments will be quicker to reach the average IT developer.
and currently I see that.
there are many people out on the edge doing MDA domain-specific languages and much more interesting stuff that.
we have not discussed during this interview.
and what I find is that.
the knowledge of these people on the edge doesn't come through to the average IT person.
and we should really be aware that.
what we know should also be brought back to the people to help them in their day-to-day business.
yeah so that is the same gap that is between IT and business like we talked about earlier.
there was a different type of gap because in this case both sides have the same formality.
they're only the one does it in the the traditional way the way that person has been doing in 10 or 20 years.
and for many IT people it's difficult to keep up with all the new technology.
and that's why they they tend to be.
a bit conservative now.
and they ate all these new things even if they appear to be.
interesting, and and cost-effective like em da índia.
so was this the hope or fear you're expressing out?
well the hope is that we will be able to get through to.
these average people.
and a fear of course is linked to that.
because the fear is well no we will not be able to.
get all of these good stuff really used by everyone in our business. well on that.
note I think that's a fine moment to bring this interview to a conclusion.
thank you very much for your time and attention and thank you.
[Music]
thanks for downloading and listening to solve the engineering radio.
software engineering radio is an educational program brought to you by hillside Europe.
if you want more information about the podcast and all the other episodes visit our website at st - radio dot length.
if you want to support us you can donate to the AC radio team via the website.
or you can advertise for su radio for example by clicking on the dick reddit delicious and slash dog buttons.
to contact the team please send email to team at SC - radio net.
or if it is specific to an episode please use the comments facility on the website so other people can react to your comments.
this episode of se radio as well as all other episodes are licensed under a creative commons 2.5 license.
please see the website for details.
thanks to Charlie Crowell and the pod safe music network for the music used in the show.
the song is called Vegas hard rock travel.
[Music]